this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hello everyone this is felina for
software engineering radio
today with me on the show dr hadley
wickham he is the chief scientist at
rstudio the leading ide for r and he's
also a junk professor of statistics
at the university of auckland stanford
university and rice university
he is the creator of the topic of
today's show the tidyverse package
which supports tidy data approach to
data import analysis and modelling nr
welcome to the show hadley hi felena
thanks for having me
so first up what is r most of our
listeners are programmers but not
statisticians
so they might have heard of r as a
programming language but
what is r what makes it unique r is a
programming language
that was designed specifically for the
needs
of statistics and data analysis so it's
been around for a while now
it's kind of the successor to a
programming language called s that was
invented
at 18t in the 70s i think late 70s early
80s
and it was sort of originally designed
to string together a bunch of c and four
transcripts on the
command line but since then it's really
grown to become this
environment very fluid and fluent data
analysis and exploration
so you say that it's a programming
language that has specific
features for statistics can you give an
example of what is a feature that
someone doing stats really needs in a
programming language so one thing that's
that's really kind of basic and
fundamental is this idea of a missing
value
so you know often you collect data and
something goes wrong and you don't know
what a specific value
is and you need some way to record that
and that's the idea of a missing value
it's kind of like a null and sequel if
you've used that
but very very few programming languages
have that kind of built in at a
fundamental level like most of them like
python and julia kind of have it added
at a higher level in the stack the other
thing just in general
is that i was really designed from kind
of day one to be this interactive
development environment so so even more
than like a scripting language
like python that the fundamental way you
use are as you type you know like a line
or a couple of lines of code
and then you look at the output and then
you think a little bit and you type some
more codes it's a very very interactive
environment
so that's a little bit like what you
might know from other programming
languages as a rappel
or is it something different exactly
exactly so do we know how popular
r is because i hear this oh r is a very
popular
language for data analysis do we have a
sense of how many users there are
i mean it's really really hard to tell
you know i think
multiple millions certainly
and then it's kind of a matter of like
picking the programming language ranking
that gives your favorite programming
language the highest
possible ranking i think it's fair to
say
now looking across a bunch of different
rankings are as one of the top 20
most popular programming languages i
think it's you know some of them show it
in the top
10 but i think it's it's up there it's
pretty popular
but it's mainly used for you know by
people doing data analysis so it's a
little bit of a
niche language like it's not a i mean it
is a general purpose programming
language in the sense that you can do
anything with
it but it is primarily used by people
doing doing data science and statistics
do you also think that like that's the
way it should be that
people doing data analysis have their
own programming languages even though
they might be
also usable for general purpose is that
a good idea
or is it would it be nicer if everyone
used the same language
yeah that's a i mean i think it would be
nice it would be nice if there was
like one programming language right that
would be wonderful like you wouldn't
have to
have different the same things developed
multiple times with different
programming languages
but of course the problem is like one
programming language can't possibly
solve every problem completely in the
way that you want it like if
you have one just one programming
language you've got to make a bunch of
compromises
and i think you'll end up with a system
where like probably no one is that happy
with it
so there's certainly downsides to having
like this kind of niche language
specifically
for pretty broad domain but i think that
the advantages of that you get something
that's
really tightly tailored to the types of
problems that you care about as a data
scientist or a statistician
yeah that makes sense and r has been
around for quite a long time
do you think r is moving more away from
being a general purpose language or is
it
adapting features to look more like a
general purpose language
that's an interesting question i think
it's not the language so much it's
changing
as the community and you know what the
community is developing
when i started using uh during my phd
which is like
15 years ago or something i was almost
exclusively used
you know by people with phds and
statistics
and there and it was very very tightly
tightly connected to doing data analysis
and so not much has changed about the
language since then
but the community has really exploded
and
in the last 15 years the kind of use
cases and the
things that people are using it for and
what they need to do their jobs is
greatly expanded
and so that you know that kind of means
things like for connecting to new types
of databases and
connecting to all sorts of the web apis
where people get data from
these days and this is just that's just
kind of meant that its strength as a
programming language have kind of
expanded in new areas so
that wasn't useful previously so then i
want to zoom in a little bit about one
specific part of
r and that's the tidy verse that you
created and designs
why did you make the tidy verse what
problem does it solve
within the problems that are already
solved i mean it solves a very
similar set of problems i think the
thing that is kind of
interesting and weird about the tidy
verses in some sense it actually like
restrains what you can do it kind of
constrains you it constricts you it
gives you like a smaller set of options
powered by some kind of like underlying
theory designed around the idea of like
really about
composition and in some sense i think
that tidy verse
is like a search for like the atoms
of data science and like how in a simple
set of techniques for combining those
atoms up into molecules
so you can like solve any problem
hopefully using this like
pretty small set of fundamental ideas
and fundamental techniques
did you make tidy first for your own use
or was it from the start already meant
as something to serve the community
so it really got started like well
before it was called the tidy verse
when i was doing my phd and as part of
my phd my assistantship was a consulting
assistantship so i helped phd students
help do the analyses for their phds
non-statistics phd students
and that was really a transformative
experience for me because i was doing my
phd in statistics at the time taking all
of these classes about
you know all these like really
complicated mathematical theory and
sophisticated models
but when it came time to actually like
help
people do their data analysis
the first problem you encounter is like
how the heck do you get the data out of
whatever form
that they've stored it in and you know
people collect data and record data in a
way that makes sense that makes it
easy as possible to record the data not
to analyze the data
and so the first problem you always hit
in every data analysis is like how the
heck do you get it from
the form they have it in into the form
that you needed and that's really what
started my journey into
the ideas of tidy data and tidying data
and reshaping data
like just how could i get how could i do
my job with these data sets that i'd
never seen before
stored in ways that frankly at the time
seemed utterly crazy to me
so what are the challenges you would say
to create a
programming language for statisticians i
think one of the challenges you just
said is
well data comes in in any format so we
have to make it fit
that's probably also where the feature
of no values comes in handy that
sometimes you have data in a in a messy
format
but what other challenges are there if
you're designing a programming system
that's made for
what we programmers would call
non-programmers people that aren't
employed as professional programmers
yeah i think that's a really
it's really interesting to contemplate
that and that's something we spend
quite a lot of time thinking about in
the tidy verse kind of trying to balance
like
how do we give like experts people have
decided to want to learn
how to master r as a programming
language and get really good at it
versus the kind of casual users of r
who certainly don't identify as
programmers that just want to do like
the
smallest possible amount of r code to
get their
jobs done and so i think like one of the
things i really believe in
is if you're not going to become a
programmer if you're not going to you
know devote hours and hours to writing a
programming language
it's really important to figure out what
those like what's the smallest set of
big ideas you know need to kind of get
into your head
most programming languages those are
ideas around like how functions work and
how objects work
but in our i think one of the big ideas
is like how does data work
this idea that we've worked on of like
tidy data like how should you
organize your data so that's going to be
easy to analyze after the fact
and i think like now i can kind of
explain it in a sentence it took like 10
years to get there
but the basic here is that you want
every column
in your rectangular data frame to be a
variable and
if you kind of look more at the theory
of tidy data you can see it has some
pretty close parallels to
card's third normal form but just like
this idea like trying to figure out like
what is this key idea
and how can we express it succinctly
in a way that like most people can
understand with like a relatively small
amount of training
that's something we spend a lot of time
thinking about i think we
might want to go one step back there
because you did mention a few things and
those everyone in the audience might be
familiar with
for example you said a rectangular data
frame
has columns within it could you
elaborate a little bit more on what that
means
the main type of data that people work
with and are is like rectangular data
so you've got rows and columns and
generally
in most cases i think to make data
analysis easy you want each column
to be a variable something that you've
measured
and each row should be an observation a
collection of related measurements
it turns out to be really difficult to
precisely describe like what a variable
is and what our observation is
but generally your kind of like everyday
language the everyday knowledge people
have of variables and observations tends
to be pretty good
once they've got that framework to
organize your data in that rectangular
way
yeah so can we give an example of an
observation an example of a variable
because
i think variable means something
slightly different here than it means
for professional programmers in the
program
about all these different this is i
think one of the one of the challenges
of teaching and particularly kind of
interdisciplinary work
is all of these words that mean like
totally different things to different
people
yeah and before i talk about what
something a data scientist thinks of
as a variable you know statisticians
have this idea
of a random variable which is
even like something even worse because
it's not a random variable is actually
like a function uh it's neither random
nor variable which seems like a really
confusing name is again totally
different to how you think about a
variable in most
programming languages so a variable
in the kind of data science sense is
something like you measure like weight
or height or age or someone's name or
like a unique identifier
these are like the columns you'd have in
database
like collections of measurements
basically that are related by these
observations so an observation
could be a like a person it could be a
person at a specific time
a person at a specific time given a
specific drug to try out
some new therapy okay i think that is
clear
so now the concepts from statistics are
a little bit more related to
databases and things programmers might
know
you said something really interesting
you said that you wanted tidy verse to
have a small set of
big ideas which i think is a great way
to design something
and i think we covered one of those big
ideas like a data frame and how do you
organize your data yeah
were there any other big ideas in your
like design
so i think another big idea is
this idea of tidy evaluation
which i think the way to understand tidy
evaluation if i
can explain it briefly is this kind of
blurring of this line between a variable
in this kind of like data science
statistical sense like something one of
those columns in the data frame
and a variable in the computer science
something like that exists and you can
work with directly
this is a like the reason why you want
to blur this line
is because you want often want to do
similar operations
to these like statistics variables as
you do
to these computer science variables like
you want to be able to say i want to
compute someone's bmi
by dividing their weight by their height
squared
for example now you're kind of combining
those two ideas of variables you're
now saying i want to create a new column
a new variable
that is a function of two existing
variables and another thing that's
interesting about r which i
haven't mentioned in most programming
languages you'd have to if you had
multiple observations
if you had the weight and height for
multiple people you would have to write
a for loop so that you'd loop over every
single person
get their weight square the height and
divide the two
whereas in r you'd express that in a
single calculation because r is
vectorized so
rather than just dealing with single
numbers it deals with vectors or
arrays of numbers so that you would just
to compute the
bmi of any number of people you just say
weight divided by height squared
and then it's automatically applied to
all the observations that you have
exactly that brings me to another
interesting question
what about scalability and performance
is this something you look at at the
programming language level because i can
imagine that
you define a simple function and then
you might not realize
that this has been calculated over
everything in your data set
you help people write efficient code is
your own engine really efficient
yeah so i think in general for myself
personally at least i spend most of my
time kind of thinking about the
efficiency of the human
like most people are dealing with like
data sets that are like small enough
that the computational cost isn't the
bottom the thing that you spend most of
your time doing
is thinking about what you need to do
next with your data and then how do you
express that in
our code so you know computational the
cost is certainly important but it's
something that i think i generally spend
like
that that's not my area of expertise i
care about like how do we make the human
as efficient as possible that means for
like me
as a developer of our packages i spend
some time rewriting my r code and the c
and z plus
plus for efficiency and doing profiling
and all the sorts of things that
programmers do in every language to make
their code fast
but by and large like that's not
something that
most eye users have to worry about
because again they're not programmers
and they're dealing with you know maybe
tens or hundreds of thousands of
observations and just doing the most
naive thing
with modern computers is fast enough
yeah so you say performance issues is
not really something that
you typically run into if you're doing
data analysis
i mean that's a little bit maybe that's
a little bit strong you
probably still run into it a little bit
but it's not the thing that i think like
dominates
most the problems are like figuring out
like what you actually want to do
um you spend like minutes hours days
thinking about that whereas the
computation might be
seconds or minutes so we want to zoom in
a little bit more into the design
decisions that went into making the tidy
verse and we talked about these big
ideas
but i'm sure at one point there were
also trade-offs where you wanted to have
two features but you couldn't have them
both or one new language feature
impacted another
language feature can you give us an
example of difficult trade-offs that you
had to make in the design process
yeah let me i think that the most
common trade-off we kind of battle with
is this tension between like experts
and casual users of our
and because we as the developer of the
packages like you know we
we live in our we're thinking about our
40 hours a week
it's very easy to kind of develop
features
that you know make us super effective
but no one else can really understand
how they work there's been a couple of
kind of recent examples
of that that come to mind the first of
this is the sort of idea of tidy
evaluation which i
i talked about briefly before where like
we came up with this like really
i think really good underlying theory
and we got really excited about it
and then we wanted to share it with the
world and frankly i thought the world
was not ready for in the world just
did not really care about it because it
was this really sort of advanced feature
that we got excited about but you know
most our developers
didn't need to the other thing that's
come up recently comes back to this idea
of vectorization like you want to do
something to every observation
without having to write some kind of for
loop and
r is a bunch of these vectorized
operations like all of the basic
mathematics you know if you want to add
or divide or multiply
trigonometry functions exponential logs
all of that all of that's kind of built
in
but sometimes you get to a point where
you have a function that's not
vectorized
and so how do you apply that
to every single observation with
something more complicated like maybe
you want to fit a model or
maybe your variable is a list of file
paths and now you want to go through
every file path that's a csv
file and read them all into one giant
file we've always
i think we're going to keep bouncing
back and forth
in some sense between like explicitness
and magic and like on the explicit side
as like
teaching people about functional
programming because ours are functional
programming language like
how do you understand the ideas behind
functional programming so you can use it
effectively
versus like how do we just give you some
magic
so you don't need to care about what's
going on behind the scenes you never
learn anything about like functions or
functions
that work with functions and you can
just kind of
do what you want and so recently in the
latest version of dplyr which is the
package
for datum manipulation we have this kind
of new row wise function which
kind of magically automatically
vectorizes things
you transform a data frame in such a way
that now every operation you perform on
it is going to be done
on each row individually the for loop
kind of happens behind the scenes
automatically
for you and this is the sort of tension
we're always thinking about like
what's too magical like when does it
work
and then i mean magic is great when it
works but when it fails you've got like
no idea what went wrong
and you've got no idea how to resolve it
versus this tension between like let's
teach you
from the ground up like what a function
is how a function works
what's a higher order function how does
that work giving you like a very kind of
detailed and correct model of the
programming language
but now you've been invest a lot of time
into learning it yeah i
really like your summary there where you
say it's a trade-off
on one end of the spectrum you have
total magic where you're happy if it
works but you don't really know why
and then on the other hand of the
spectrum you have explicitness where you
have to really
detail every step you take which is a
lot of work but then also
you have a lot of control i think that's
a struggle that many people that make
software for other people
also recognize and this sort of comes
back to like this idea like what are the
big ideas like what are the things that
we really believe
you have to learn before you can do this
stuff
correctly and like safely and correctly
and efficiently
and we want to keep that as small as
possible so you can kind of
get into it as quickly as possible get
some wins so you enjoy the process of
learning
but at the same time we don't want to
just say like you know it's a free-fall
did there's some important like
infrastructure some foundation you need
to build up over time so you can
you know have a good mental model of
what's going on and
and make better decisions in the future
yeah and it totally makes sense
has there been any features that you
implemented and then later regret it
where you thought oh
people don't understand or they misuse
this wasn't the way
i wanted people to apply things yeah
so i now have my kind of over time like
my criteria for success of the system
has changed
and now one of my criterias for success
is that a package is not successful
until someone has used it to commit
academic thought
so i you know i think that's the
fundamental challenge of like developing
general tools like if you want
people to do like solve new problems
with them you have to accept
that they might do things that you think
are fundamentally wrong
and that's the sort of trade-off between
freedom and safety and if you can strain
people to the sort of like single path
where they can only do what you want
that's pretty limiting and there's lots
of things that you didn't think of that
might be really important
generally like i'm not too worried about
that now i think you just have to accept
that that people are gonna do things
that you don't agree with and you can't
kind of control that at the software
level i think if you
the best you can do is to kind of
control that at like a social level and
you know be like a positive role model
and show people how to use these tools
ethically and correctly but you you
can't kind of put that in at a
fundamental level
can you give an example of a feature
that has been used for academic frauds
intentionally or accidentally i forget
the name of the
guy but he did this pretty
study he sort of faked a bunch of data
for his phd he got some pretty famous
paper out of it
and made like these most beautiful
graphics
using ggplot2 they were like very very
compelling graphics
but really they're not really like
scientific graphics they're basically
propaganda
because that the underlying data was
made up
has there been any feature that you had
to change
yeah yes a lot of can you give an
example
that's something we spend a lot of time
thinking about now like how do we
change things that we've done before so
i think that the arc of tidy data is
kind of a good one to
to talk about that because they've been
working on tools to help you tidy your
data so to go from whatever form
you've currently got it into this form
that you've got each variable as a
column and each row is an observation
and that's something that i've been like
working on i don't know for like 15
years
now and they've been like four i think
four major changes in the way that i
think about that so they've been over
the course
of those 15 years there's been a package
called reshape
another package called reshape2 another
package called tidier and most recently
two new functions and tidier pivot
longer and pivot wider
which is a sort of culmination of a
bunch of changes a bunch of feedback
over time people saying like
they couldn't understand the functions
or every time they use the function
they'd look up the documentation they
just didn't stick in people's head
and so that's something like i find like
that's one of the things that i love
like twitter for because you just
you can get a stream of of things that
like people will probably never mention
to you in person but like complain about
so would you say that's the biggest
reason to change a feature that it's
hard to understand for people because i
think that's what you said there that
you had to change things because
people would have to look up the syntax
or they would they would do it wrongly
every time
yeah i think like particularly for what
i care about which is sort of
facilitating non-programmers
to do data science to do data analysis
in a programming language yeah that's
really important
this is on other people either this is
like me as well like i would use these
functions which i wrote
some time ago and i couldn't remember
how they work and i would have to read
the documentation every time as well
at the time made total sense to me like
i have this experience a lot like i'm
programming something like wow this is
amazing like this
this totally makes sense this is a great
way to think about the problem
and then i come back to it like three
months later and i have like literally
no idea
what i was thinking you know that's very
much the experience of like a new
program right they come to this like
absolutely fresh they've got
a few preconceptions and if it doesn't
stick in their brain
i think that that can be a sign that
there's something wrong with the design
of the function you know i'd love to
hear more about
how you get our feedback so you just
mentioned that oh people on twitter they
complain or maybe they send you
compliments of things they like
i guess you also still use your own
tools to do some data analysis
what are other ways that you gather
feedback to know the direction of the
language
yeah we do like a surprisingly small
amount of kind of like
quantitative feedback so relatively
recently we've started doing a few more
like very casual
surveys which are mostly like we'll just
tweet out a question
and point you to a google form and get
sort of feedback on things
help both in terms of like trying to
figure out what are common problems
people are facing anything to try out
like here are four possible solutions
which one of those kind of resonates
with you
and you know this is always a little
tricky because we want to try and
see what's going to stick in your heads
like in three months time and like
measuring that is very very tricky the
other thing that i think is really hard
is people don't know what they need
and it's very difficult to kind of
recognize
that there's a bunch of like maybe
things in disparate areas that if you
had one tool or one
another big idea that helped you solve
all those problems
like to me like that's the thing that
we're looking for like what are these
big ideas
and you know people don't know what they
don't know and they
it's very hard to articulate that i
think some of what we do i think is just
inventing
words for new topics because if you
don't have a name for a topic it's
really hard to talk about it
and this i think was one of the one of
the ideas of like
tidy data that's been so impactful is
just having this idea like
this name of tidy data and yeah you
could talk about like i'm
tidying my data my data isn't tidy this
data is tidy
and so how like one of the things that i
think is really important is like trying
to discover these things that need
names and like i have
no idea how to do that really except to
talk to a bunch of different people and
try and keep my eyes open
for repeated patterns yeah that's really
interesting because we say you do data
analysis but that's still
relatively broad i can imagine that
probably you have different
types of users like maybe a biologist
does data analysis different from a
linguist or different from a computer
scientist
is this something you see where
different subfields of science have
different
uses better patterns for data analysis
and for tidy verses as well
so most i mean i think there's a huge
amount of commonality particularly at
the early phases
which we kind of focus on like getting
the data in getting it tidied and doing
like a bunch of visualizations so you
can figure out what's going on
like that's hugely similar across fields
and that said you know people in
different fields give all these the same
things different names and
attack things in slightly different ways
but i think at that level
you know there's a huge huge amount of
commonality things tend to get a little
bit different like in terms of the
detail like precisely what
visualizations are you going to put on a
paper or what models are you going to
use
there's a lot more variation in kind of
the customs
of an academic field or subfield
but that tends to be something that i
spend my time
so much time thinking about so it is
similar enough
like what every scientist does in terms
of data analysis is similar enough that
you don't need separate packages for
being a biologist or a computer
scientist
i think some parts you do because you're
going to deal with like the certain
types of
data file that only biologists deal with
and
you know computer scientists if you're
publishing and if you're publishing a
paper and vis you know there are models
that people are going to expect that you
to use or that you
you know that reviewers are going to
understand
and be easy to sell on so certainly like
this maybe 20
of the analysis is very specific to a
given domain and every
domain needs a bunch of different
specialized tools for that
but like there is a solid 80 at the
heart of it
that is the same like that's just about
data and working with data and it
doesn't matter what field you're in
and how does the tidy version r compare
to other tools for data analysis
of course if i think about data analysis
i think of something like excel
or maybe in python you have appendas
which i think shares some of the big
ideas of the tiny version in terms of
data frames and stuff like that and
missing values
so how would you say r compares to
alternatives for data analysis
yeah so you kind of identify the two big
families of alternatives which are like
point-and-click guise and other
programming languages
i think if you want to call yourself a
data scientist i think like one of the
distinctions between data science and
data analysis generally
is that data science is done in a
programming language
because i think programming languages
have this kind of immense advantage
that they are just text you represent
the sequence of operations you're
performing in text
and text is like amazingly powerful
because you can like google it you can
copy and paste it you can email
you can turn your problems into
something that you put on an email and
see them somewhere else
and then of course it's all like
re-runnable and reproducible
so i think if you are someone who like
no of course there's a big disadvantage
to programming languages well the big
advantage of a gui is kind of everything
is spelled out in front of you you've
got all these
menus and these buttons and maybe you
can't like remember what they all do
but you can kind of like search through
them all of your options are laid out in
front of you
whereas with a programming language like
you have to remember what you can do and
string all the pieces together
so guise i think are great like for
casual users for people who aren't doing
data science enough to like remember
what all the commands are
but i think programming languages for
data are the kind of one of the key
distinguishing features of data science
yeah because they are text based and
that helps you do diffing and storing
and
reproducibility i mean
and it might be again this trade-off
between explicitness and magic in a
certain sense where a gui adds lots of
magic
it does a lot for you without maybe
knowing a lot
whereas in text you can be really
explicit which is nice for example for
reproducibility
perspectives yeah and then the downside
of the gui too is you're kind of
fundamentally constrained by what the
author
of the gui wanted to allow you to do it
if you want to break
out of that and do something different
it tends to be very very difficult
yeah yeah then you probably still have
to script it yourself using a
programming language within a gui if
that is allowed
exactly no i mean excel is kind of an
interesting case because it's not
just a gui it is really a programming
language and
i remember when i was in i guess i
wasn't i would have been in high school
that
someone showed me a rotating 3d
plot that that made in excel and my my
mind was just
not using visual basic or anything but
just constructing
in cell formulas to do all of the
trigonometry
to rotate the cloud of points in 3d and
my mind was just
just blown yeah it is pretty amazing
what you can do with excel but indeed it
does suffer from some of the limitations
where
it's harder to version control for
example it's harder to
email your calculations to someone yeah
i also remember like when i
taught briefly taught a class that was
r excel and sas sas is one of the kind
of
older like very specialized programming
languages specifically for statistics
and one of the things that i found
really interesting is that it was
actually quite difficult for me to teach
or to show people what i was doing in
excel
because there's a you know a bunch of
things with like a tiny difference in
what you do with a mouse makes a big
difference like are you right-clicking
or are you left-clicking are you
double-clicking
like sometimes like when you're dragging
certain things just like being off by a
pixel or two
gives you a completely different result
that sort of opened my eyes so like
i've been a big excel user for a long
time but just trying to show other
people what i was doing
was really really difficult whereas with
r i could always like copy and paste it
and like put it into a file that you
could
run you could do exactly the same thing
i did on your computer
yeah and given the reproducibility
crisis in science
where i mean sometimes it might be
people that accidentally just forgot how
their spreadsheet works because it was
years ago but
sometimes also they're fraud involved
this does seem like a very important
feature nowadays
yeah i think the other thing that's sort
of interesting and i guess there's one
other style of programming which
has its proponents and data science it's
a sort of drag and drop
component visual programming style where
you like have a bunch of
boxes which each represent an operation
and you connect them together with
lines and i think like that has like a
lot of the
weaknesses of programming without having
all the strengths like you're given this
tool that can do anything you're just
creating a
a graph of arbitrary complexity but you
have no longer have all of these tools
that
programmers have around like diffing and
debugging
and emailing to people to get their help
i think like that because of
communication side of code is really
really really important
i also want to zoom in a little bit
about the technical side of r in a tidy
verse so how does it work technically is
it like a compiled language or an
interpreted language
so it's an interpreted language although
like as
a package developer of r we also package
the valves in general also write
under the hood r is written in c and so
you can also
write c code if you want to switch into
a you know a language designed for
for much higher performance but yeah are
fundamentally interpreted kind of
interactive language
really designed around the ripple so you
ask a question of your data and get your
answer back
as quickly as possible and if you would
write extensions or modules would you
typically
then write our modules in r or do people
then fall back to see
i think the vast majority of so in
our community like we call from packages
into libraries or modules so the vast
majority of packages are written in r
i think the two main reasons to write
them and see
is i like either performance or because
you're connecting to some other
pre-existing software library that's
been written in c
you know so for example like the r
package that works with xml data
is basically just a binding to live xml2
so it just provides an interface so the
user can write r code that calls c
code that calls a c code written by
other people to to do all the usual
things you want to do the xml
that's an interesting point that brings
me to a next question like how does r
interoperate with other systems you just
said oh you can
load xml data can you also embed it with
other programming languages like
can i have some statistic analysis in r
on the front-end with javascript or
something like that
yeah i think so that really like
historically
like r was this kind of glue language
between c and fortran and that's i think
a really
big part of ours dna this also comes
back to your question about kind of
performance that
in some ways the point of r is not to be
a like really fast programming language
but it should be able to talk to really
fast programming languages
really easily so obviously there's like
really strong connections to the stuff
you want to do for data for like
databases and xml and json
and there's really strong connections to
c and fortran from a sort of statistical
history
more recently connections in both
directions to python
some people have experimented with
starting to use
rust to write their high performance
packages
and then of course a bunch of
connections to javascript mostly
from r2 javascript one of the things
that my colleagues at r studio work on
is this this tool called shiny
which makes it really easy for an r
programmer to basically make a web app
and then all of the javascript
you know there's a lot of communication
with javascript going on behind the
scenes
so then that will allow you to create
maybe an interactive visualization on
the website
based on data analysis done in r yeah
exactly
the other thing we see it used for a lot
is kind of this like historically
if you're producing a report for someone
you know you would want to make sure
you've produced every possible graph
that they might ask for and so you just
give them this like 800 page pdf that
has every possible graph they might ever
ask for
which is obviously not a wonderful user
experience
and so now we're seeing people kind of
transition to using shiny apps for that
as a data scientist you can give the
person who needs to understand the data
and make decisions based on that
you can give them some kind of like
limited analysis ability so they can try
out a few different scenarios they can
ask different questions of the data
so that is the scenario where you have
data analysis in r and then you
project it to another programming
language like javascript
what about reverse where you build maybe
something like a web app that's
collecting data that's running your
experiment
and then can you get your data back into
r and run a live data analysis
yes so one of the things that the kind
of live data that i'm most familiar with
that we use a lot
internally as google sheets so we'll
collect data like using a google form
which will go into google sheet or maybe
we'll be doing data entry and google
sheets
directly because it's such a like
fantastic like collaborative environment
so we for example we're working on our
studio global our online conferences is
coming up soon
we in the program committee we use
google sheets a lot because we can have
a live you can we can have a meeting
and then you know three of us are
entering data into a google sheet and
then we have an r script that pulls that
into r
like does some like basic sanity
checking like
have we scheduled multiple things at the
same time like if we made one person
give
seven talks all that that kind of stuff
and that's just a really nice
pattern that's kind of like using like
google sheets but what it's really good
at and using r for what it's really good
at
and having this like live live update
where you can easily see what's happened
after you've made some changes to your
data
yeah that's certainly that glue
functionality that you talked about
before where r is the glue between
something that collects data and someone
that wants to look at data
absolutely so what are your big plans
for the future
what features are you working on what
trends are you excited about
i think generally it feels like we
generally have this sort of like
punctuated equilibrium like where we
go through periods of like rapid fairly
moderately large change and then periods
where we just kind of like let the dust
title
let people learn about what's changed
recently
and it feels like we're coming sort of
out of that period of a bunch of change
and
into a period where we are like
consolidating
we're improving our educational
materials we're like making sure
we've like smoothed all the rough sharp
corners off all of our functions so as
easy as possible
again this is sort of one of the things
that can rely on twitter for is like
just in general like how is the
community like feeling about
change right now do people want like big
new things that they're gonna have to
learn about
or might make their lives better but
it's going to require some
investment or do they want to stay where
they basically are
and i think kind of the message we're
getting at the moment
lots of change going on elsewhere in the
world that
people basically i think i just just
want to stay where they are
and have the rough corners polished down
make everything like fit together a
little more tightly
better error messages fewer error
messages all that kind of stuff
are there any features in other
programming languages or other ides or
programming systems that you're like
jealous about you're like oh i wish
we could also have that or i wish i had
the time to implement that idea
into thai diverse and then like very
very kind of
big side of things that things will take
us if we ever did start and that would
take us multiple years like i love
the idea of kind of of sort of like type
inference and
bringing in kind of gradual typing and
the way that php and
ruby and other languages have so you can
start to be a little bit more explicit
about what types of data you expect your
function to take in
and to produce and that is a bunch of
like benefits from performance to
documentation to error messages to
testing that that just seems like
something i would love like
like haskell has or rust has unless or
extent just
stuff like that that allow you to make
it more explicit more clear like
what are the inputs and outputs of your
function are
and then do you not implement that
because it's too much work or because it
doesn't really fit the language i can
imagine that if you have this
missing data type that that makes type
inference really hard
if that's allowed then you need some
sort of null type that
over arcs all the other types yes i
think the biggest thing is like there's
clearly a large amount of work
and it's not clear exactly what the
payoff is like i think it would be
really cool
but would that actually help enough
people to justify you know spending
probably
two or three programming years worth of
work on it
and you know this in general is my my
personal challenges there's lots of like
really cool programming things that i
love
and think are really awesome and amazing
and would be fascinating to explore in
more detail
but i'm not sure whether anyone else
would really care about them that much
or whether that actually have a positive
impact on most people's lives
yeah that is hard to know of course if a
new feature really makes something
better like you just had better error
messages like
what is better like more detail might
help some programmers but might actually
harm the productivity of other
developers because then i have to read
the
entire error message which might not be
so useful so how do you know if a new
language feature is better
is it just good feeling because you said
before that
you didn't really do any build surveys
yeah i mean it's mostly i think it's
like a combination of gut feeling
like sort of trying it out and then
seeing
how it feels to us as like data
analysts and then you know just talking
like bringing into the community and
kind of saying like how does this
like feel to you but it's a really
really
even if we did kind of invest
significantly
it's not clear to me like how you even
measure the things that we care about
at least i realize like one metric that
i care about
is kind of time spent and flow state
like i think in some ways that's the key
metric i would love to optimize
like i want you to be in flow state
where you
are like getting code out of your brains
your fingers are just like typing our
code you have to think about it
relatively little
you're fluent you're not searching your
brain
like that's kind of what i want to
optimize but like
how on earth do you measure that and
then how do you
kind of like measure it's not just like
in the moment
it's like a combination of how long it
takes to learn it all
and to get into that place where you can
do this it's really really
really hard yeah this is what sometimes
languages programming language designers
called like the language gets out of the
way
you just allow the user to program and
the language isn't
giving you an annoying pull purpose like
oh you know this type doesn't match what
you're doing here
really it's almost like the programming
language isn't there and you can just
express your thoughts directly but
that is really hard to acquire of course
in a programming language yeah
but there's also at the same time like
the programming language also has to
like help
shape your thinking in a way that kind
of guides you
naturally towards a path that's more
likely to be successful and
again i just have like no i i mean how
you do that is really really tough
it does really feel like a kind of an
art or a craft not a science right now
yeah it does seem even though you say
that you don't really know how to do it
it does seem like you're doing really
well because the toilet versus a really
popular
our package and it has supported many
statisticians and also
other scientists over the years in doing
lots of data analysis
yeah i mean i think we've been like
pretty successful i think we managed to
do quite a good job
like i don't know how we do it i think
we've done it enough successfully that
doesn't seem to be
it's not just luck but i don't know
exactly what it is that
like how we think about this problem
like what are the skills we bring to
beer that are really the most useful
yeah it might be a combination of
experience you have
scientists yourself really doing a phd
doing data analysis and then
getting to know the problem space really
well and then designing something that
does seem to be key i think
yeah the other thing that that's
interesting to me as i kind of
get more senior in age is
as sort of new folks join my team
it's clear like my there's people on
my team and in the community in the
world whose kind of raw programming
power
is much like greater than mine they can
tune out
code much faster than i can but somehow
i have this like ability
the skill that i have is seeing like two
or three steps down the road
and being like oh these two different
things are gonna have this kind of
conflict
you're gonna run into problems in like
months time if you continue down this
path
that's just a really it's interesting to
see like how
where your skills are when you work
closely with other people who are like
very very
very talented yeah and i would say
that's probably due to your experience
in
working with these types of systems and
having developed them that
you don't need to be the most efficient
programmer but if you can in need
envision
what features people might like how they
might combine together then
that is very interesting yeah which is
not to say i don't still spend a lot of
time on dating and writing a bunch of
code that
uh i eventually throw out but i think
that's the other thing i've become more
comfortable with
over time is just accepting that like
creating something good
is often about like throwing out stuff
throwing out things that you've spent
potentially a lot of time on whether
that's like code
or writing or i think even like
if like baking like the way that people
present
like these beautiful trays of cookies is
that there's also like another tray of
really ugly cookies that you never get
to see
yeah and probably also like a hundred
trays of cookies in their past
that they think they were only just a
little bit happy about yeah exactly and
it's very
like you can't see that like it's very
hard to see that from the outside
you look at someone and you see you see
all the things that they've been
successful at and presented to the
public you don't see all the things that
i've
i've tried and experiments that did not
succeed
yeah that's true hey if that was all i
wanted to ask is there anything that we
missed anything where you say oh i
really want to share
this and this fact about the die divorce
i don't think so i mean
the main thing is if you're kind of
interested in learning more and tidyvis
has a website
of course and there's also a book that i
co-wrote with garrett groman called
after data science
which is like really our attempts to
take someone potentially hasn't
programmed at all and help them become
competent happy data scientists
in r so that's available online for free
you can just google alpha data science
and
get the details there yeah we'll put the
link to r and the tidy verse and also to
your book in the show note so
people can easily find them is there
anywhere else we can find you on the web
are you on twitter do you blog
yeah twitter i'm mostly on twitter i
must spend probably too much time on
twitter
just as happy with him i don't have a
personal blog where we have a team
tidy vest blog if that's a tidy verse or
that's the best place
yeah i think that's mostly of interest
if you use the tidy verse because that's
where we post
all the release announcements that's
where we kind of post
important like hey we're thinking about
making this really big change like
please give us feedback
kind of things i think that's that's a
great place to hang out if you're
familiar if you use the titles
frequently great so make sure that we
will also link to the 21st blog and tune
your twitter
account in the show notes thank you so
much for being on the show hadley
well thanks velena thanks for having me
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website
at se-radio.net to provide feedback you
can comment on each episode on the
website or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening